<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <letter n="1">[Letter from <writer>Marian Baldwin</writer>, <date>June 30,
            <year>1917</year></date>] <title>On Board La Touraine,</title>
        <date>June 30th, <year>1917</year></date>. <p>Even now that we are out of sight of land, it
            seems impossible that I am actually off to <location>France</location> and, for the
            first time in my life, traveling alone. Everything has happened so quickly since the
            American Fund for French Wounded found an opening for me in <location>Paris</location>
            that I suppose I am still somewhat <feel>dazed and bewildered</feel>. The fact that I
            don't know what it will all be like and that I can't look ahead makes it easier to be
                <feel>happy and live</feel> in the present. Of course I have had a bit of a taste in
                <location>New York</location> of the work that the A. F. F. W. is doing but its
            Headquarters in Paris will be different in some ways I fancy.</p>
        <p>I can't get over how <feel>lucky</feel> I am to have this chance for I realize how few
            girls of my age are getting across, and I understood the <feel>grit and pluck</feel>
            which made you encourage me on my great adventure and send me along a path which has
            proved so dangerous of late.</p>
        <p>As we drifted down the river, in the sunset glow with two absurd tugs puffing alongside,
            I know that many eyes were moist and that the same thought was in all our minds. How
            many of this ship's company will see that sky-line again! It was very quiet, no one
            spoke much, and, little by little, the glow faded from the sky and one star after
            another appeared. I knew that you would be looking at those same stars down in
                <location>Lakewood</location> and that your thoughts and prayers were the same that
            filled my heart at that moment. Somehow distance does not separate, after all.</p>
        <p>We waited near the <location>Statue of Liberty</location> until midnight—a rumor had it
            that a "personage" was to come on board. This individual was shrouded in mystery until
            we put to sea when it was given out that the party which had clambered aboard in the
            night was none other than the Italian Mission. Our spirits rose at once for, what with
            Frank Sayre on the boat and these distinguished Italian gentlemen, we shall doubtless be
            honored by a bigger convoy and so doubly safe. However, thus far we have but two
            destroyers following us. They can be seen distinctly outlined against the horizon, one
            on each side, and seem to be the same somber gray which all ships are affecting in this
            war. A sailor informed me this morning that we weren't in much danger for the first four
            or five days but that after that I might see some <feel>excitement</feel>. Here's
            hoping!</p>
        <p>I have a small inside cabin and my room-mate is quite a character. She is a native of
                <location>Haiti</location>, <feel>voluble and very portly</feel>—has four large
            pieces of baggage in our tiny stateroom, wears a costume which resembles a Mother
            Hubbard and smokes countless thin cigarettes that smell like incense! When I appeared,
            there didn't seem to be much room for me but, as she says, luckily I am small, and I was
            soon tucked into the upper berth with my belongings! She really isn't bad and after
            looking me over <train>car</train>efully told me that she didn't think we would fight
            and from that time has beamed upon me! She is going over to join her son who has been
            fighting with the French since the beginning of the war but will never go back to the
            Front now, having lost some fingers off each hand. She is so thankful, she says, that he
            hasn't lost more than his fingers. </p>
        <pubinfo>[Source: _Canteening Overseas_: <year>1917-1919</year>, published
            <year>1920</year>.] </pubinfo>
    </letter>
    <letter n="2"><poi>En route from <location>Bordeaux</location> to
            <location>Paris</location></poi>, <date>July 18th, <year>1917</year></date>. <para> On
            landing yesterday I went straight to the <poi>Hôtel de France</poi> and it certainly was
            good to have room to turn around in: as for a bed with real springs I greeted it with
                <feel> enthusiasm</feel>! Towards evening <pers>Frank and I</pers> took a long
                <act>walk</act> about the city. A <poi>port town</poi> always <feel>interests
                me</feel> and we saw it all at the <desc>loveliest time</desc> of day. The
                <poi>harbor</poi> was full of fishing smacks and small craft of all kinds and
                <desc>exquisite tones</desc> in the <poi>sails and rigging</poi>. The last rays of
            the sun <desc>cast a rosy hue over everything</desc>, making one think at once of
                <location>Venice</location> and the days before the war. Later we wandered through
            some of the oldest parts of <location>Bordeaux</location> and I really<feel> felt that I
                was abroad again</feel>! The <desc>narrow winding streets</desc> and cobblestones,
            with here and there an <desc>ancient façade</desc> or doorway and everywhere, in the
                <desc>poorest alleys</desc>, a bit of a vine or potted plant in the windows. How do
            they manage to make it all so picturesque and alluring?</para>
        <para><pers>The women and the old men</pers> are doing everything and it is
                <feel>surprising</feel> to see the <pers>lady conductors</pers>. On this
                <train>train </train>they use women entirely, even in the dining <train>car</train>.
            The war hasn't robbed them of <desc>vivacity or their beautiful complexions</desc> and I
            believe they are even <desc>prettier</desc> in their simple black working clothes than
            before.</para>
        <para>We are at present passing through the <poi>famous vineyards</poi> and I have never
            seen the country look so <desc>beautiful</desc>. The crops seem in <desc>perfect
                condition</desc>, thanks to the patient labor of these <desc>wonderful</desc> women,
            and the grain waves in profusion everywhere. I have <feel>longed for you</feel> at every
            turn, how you would enjoy it all. The poppies are in <desc>their prime and, as the
                    <train>train </train>whirls by, they look like immense splashes of red -almost
                like stains of blood against the gold of the wheat.</desc></para>
        <para>I have just come in from a very <desc>excellent</desc> meal in the dining
                <train>car</train> -the food was served promptly by <pers>two French girls</pers> of
            the <desc>peasant type and with a speed</desc> that was <desc>wonderful</desc>, the
                <train>car</train> holding over thirty persons.</para>
        <location>Paris</location></letter>
    <letter n="3"><location>Bordeaux</location>, <date>December 27th, <year>1917</year>.</date>
        <para> Such <desc>crowded busy hours</desc> as we have put in during the last few days.
            However, there will be a bit of a breathing spell now, as there are to be <desc>fewer
                men</desc> in on leave until <date>New Year's</date>. This afternoon <pers>Aunt
                T</pers>. is coming to see my <desc>hideous little room</desc>. I have<act> built a
                fire</act> that is much too large for my <desc>diminutive fire-place</desc>, and we
            are to have <act>tea and cake</act>! So you see it is to be a <act>regular house
                warming</act>.</para>
        <para> I don't know whether I have written you about <poi>my sleeping apartment</poi>
            before. At any rate, it is on the<desc> top floor of a tall thin house</desc>. It was
            the only place I could get and so I have thought it <feel>wiser to laugh</feel> at its
            disadvantages. There is no coal, and wood costs six francs for eight pieces so one just
            goes without except on special occasions like to-day. I generally <act>get in</act> from
                <poi>the canteen</poi> about <time>11:30 P. M</time>. and then my <act>four flights
                seem a bit of a climb</act>, but it is nice to have a little spot of your own and
            I'm always so<feel> glad</feel> to get to the top of the stairs. I still have struggles
            with my hot water bag, for I can always see my breath in the room and I think "old
            faithful" has gotten a bit discouraged and doesn't think it worth while to keep warm in
            this damp penetrating clime.</para>
        <para> The room is<desc> papered in a mud-colored tone of gold, beetle-shaped figures
                scattered over it at intervals of two inches</desc>! I have a black iron bedstead
            and a fire-place and mantelpiece made of the black and white mottled marble that is used
            for tombstones! There are two windows, but unfortunately one <act>can't look out</act>
            as they are made of <desc>red and navy blue stained glass</desc>. However, I am very
                <feel>fond</feel> of my little room and to-day it wears a <desc>gay and festive
                look</desc> in anticipation of <act>my party</act>. I have <act>put all my
                photographs out and we are going to have a <feel>fine cozy</feel> time</act> I
            know.</para></letter>
</root>
