<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<poem>
    <title>Leaves</title>
    <author>Lloyd Schwartz</author> - <year>1941</year>- 
    <stanza s="1">1 </stanza>
    <para>Every <month>October</month> it becomes important, no, necessary to <act>see the
                <leaf>leaves</leaf></act> turning, to be <act>surrounded by
            <leaf>leaves</leaf></act> turning; it's not just the symbolism, to confront in the death
        of the year <sub>your </sub>death, one <desc>blazing</desc>
        <act>farewell appearance</act>, though the irony isn't lost on <sub>you that </sub>nature is most
            <act>seductive when it's about to die</act>, flaunting the dazzle of its incipient exit,
        an ending that at least so far the effects of human progress (pollution, acid rain) have not
        yet <emo>frightened</emo> <sub>you enough </sub>to make <sub>you believe </sub>is real; that is, <sub>you know </sub>this
        ending is a deception because of course nature is always renewing itself— the
            <tree>trees</tree> don't die, <person>they just pretend, go out in style, and return in
            style: a new style.</person></para>
    <stanza s="2">2 </stanza>
    <Para>Is it deliberate how far they make <sub>you go </sub>especially if <sub>you live </sub>in the city to get far
        enough away from home to see not just <tree>trees</tree> but only <tree>trees</tree>? The
            <desc>boring highways, roadsigns, high speeds, 10-axle trucks passing <sub>you as </sub>if they
            were in an even greater hurry than <sub>you to </sub>look at <leaf>leaves</leaf></desc>: so <sub>you
 </sub>       drive in <emo>terror</emo> for literal hours and it looks like rain, or snow, but it's
        probably just <cloud>clouds</cloud> (too <cloud>cloudy</cloud> to see any color?) and <sub>you
 </sub>       wonder, given the poverty of <sub>your </sub>memory, which road had the most color last year, but it
        doesn't matter since <sub>you're </sub>probably too late anyway, or too early— whichever road <sub>you take
 </sub>       will be the wrong one and <sub>you've </sub>probably come all this way for nothing.</Para>
    <stanza s="3">3 </stanza>
    <para>You'll be driving along <emo>depressed</emo> when suddenly a <person><cloud>cloud</cloud>
            will move and the sun will muscle through and ignite the hills</person>. It may not
        last. Probably won't last. But for a moment the whole world comes to. <person>Wakes
            up</person>. Proves it lives. It lives— <color>red, yellow, orange, brown, russet,
            ocher, vermilion, gold</color>. Flame and rust. <desc>Flame and rust, the permutations
            of burning</desc>. You're on fire. Your eyes are on fire. It won't last, <sub>you don't </sub>want
        it to last. You can't stand any more. But <sub>you don't </sub>want it to stop. It's what <sub>you've </sub>come
        for. It's what <sub>you'll </sub>come back for. It won't stay with <sub>you, </sub>but <sub>you'll </sub>remember that it
        felt like nothing else <sub>you've </sub>felt or something <sub>you've </sub>felt that also didn't last.</para>
    <foot>Copyright © <year>1992</year> by <author>Lloyd Schwartz</author>. From <book>Goodnight,
            Gracie</book> (The University of Chicago Press, <year>1992</year>). Appears courtesy of
        the author.</foot>
</poem>
