<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <title>Kue Nastar (Indonesian Pineapple Tarts)</title>
    <authorinfo><name part="first">Scott</name>
        <name part="last">Suchman</name> for <publisher>The Washington Post</publisher></authorinfo>
    <date>JAN 20th, 2022</date>
    <description>Kue nastar is a filled cookie popular in Indonesia at Tahun Bahru Imlek (Lunar New
        Year) and other holidays, such as Lebaran (Eid Mubarak) and Hari Natal (Christmas). Kue
        means cake, and the Dutch-influenced treat gets its name from the Indonesian word for
        pineapple “nanas” and the Dutch “taart,” hence “nastar.” </description>
    <background>Cookbook author Patricia Tanumihardja learned how to make the dish from her mother’s
        friend, tante (meaning "auntie") Linda Lee. Using Lee’s recipe as a foundation, Tanumihardja
        developed her own version, which uses salted butter, as well as a blend of all-purpose flour
        and cornstarch for a melt-in-your-mouth pastry. </background>
    <timeneed> Active time: <time>2 hours 30 mins</time>; Total time:<time> 9 hours</time>, with
        chilling time</timeneed>

    <prep>Make Ahead: The filling needs to be made at least <time>8 hours</time> and the dough, at
        least <time>30 minutes</time>, in advance of baking the cookies.</prep>

    <storage>Storage Notes: The filling can be refrigerated in an airtight container for up to<time>
            1 week</time>; the dough for up to <time>2 days</time>. The tarts can be stored in an
        airtight container at room temperature for up to <time>4 weeks</time>.</storage>

    <size>SERVINGS: 48 Tested size: 48 servings; tarts</size>

    <ingredients>INGREDIENTS <filling> FOR THE PINEAPPLE FILLING <measure><num num="1"
                >1</num></measure><gred> medium pineapple</gred>
            <mass>(2 to 3 pounds/907 to 1360 grams)</mass>,<conditon> peeled, cored and cut into
                1-inch cubes (about 6 <unit>cups</unit>)</conditon>
            <measure><num num=".75">3/4</num>
                <unit>cup</unit></measure>
            <mass>(150 grams)</mass>
            <gred>granulated sugar</gred>
            <measure> One (<num num="2"> 2</num>-inch)</measure>
            <gred>cinnamon stick</gred>
            <measure><num num="4">4</num></measure>
            <gred>whole cloves</gred>
            <option> Water, as needed</option></filling>
        <dough> FOR THE DOUGH <measure><num num="3.33">3 1/3</num>
                <unit>cups</unit></measure>
            <mass>(400 grams)</mass>
            <gred>all-purpose flour</gred>
            <measure>
                <num num=".5"> 1/2</num>
                <unit>cup plus <num num="2">2</num> tablespoons</unit></measure>
            <mass>(90 grams)</mass>
            <gred>cornstarch</gred>
            <measure>
                <num num="21">21</num>
                <unit>tablespoons</unit></measure>
            <mass>(10 1/2 ounces/300 grams)</mass>
            <gred>salted butter</gred>, <condition>at room temperature</condition>
            <measure><num num=".5">1/2</num>
                <unit>cup</unit></measure>
            <mass>(153 grams)</mass>
            <gred>condensed milk</gred>,<conditon> at room temperature</conditon>
            <measure><num num="3">3</num></measure>
            <gred>large egg yolks</gred>,<conditon> at room temperature, divided</conditon>
            <measure><num num="1">1</num>
                <unit>teaspoon</unit></measure>
            <gred>honey</gred>
            <measure><num num="1">1</num>
                <unit>teaspoon</unit></measure>
            <gred>warm water</gred></dough></ingredients>

    <steps>DIRECTIONS <step1> Make the pineapple filling: In the pitcher of a blender, process the
            pineapple until it forms a coarse puree, making sure no large chunks remain. </step1>
        <step2> In a 12-inch, heavy-bottomed skillet, or a large pot, such as a 8-quart Dutch oven,
            over medium-high heat, combine the pineapple puree, sugar, cinnamon and cloves and bring
            to a boil. Decrease the heat to medium-low, so the mixture is at a gentle simmer, and
            cook uncovered, stirring occasionally, until it turns dark tan and is thick, <time>1 to
                1 1/2 hours</time>. The mixture should be thick enough to roll into balls. Stir more
            frequently in the last <time>30 minutes</time> of cooking to prevent the bottom from
            burning, reducing the heat if necessary. <condition>If the mixture starts to burn, add
                water, <measure><num num="1">1</num>
                    <unit>teaspoon</unit> at a time</measure>, scraping bits from the bottom of the
                pot.</condition>
        </step2>
        <step3> Remove from the heat, let cool to the touch, <time>about 15 minutes</time>, remove
            the cloves and cinnamon stick, and transfer to a lidded container. Refrigerate for at
            least <time>8 hours and up to 1 week</time>. You should have about <measure><num
                    num="1.33">1 1/3</num>
                <unit>cups</unit></measure>
            <mass>(about 380 grams)</mass>. </step3>
        <step4> Make the dough: Into a medium bowl, sift the <gred>flour and cornstarch</gred>. </step4>
        <step5> In a large bowl and with a flexible spatula, stir together the <gred>butter</gred>
            and <gred>condensed milk</gred> until combined. Add 2 of the <gred>yolks</gred> and stir
            until well combined. The mixture will be lumpy. </step5>
        <step6> Add the flour mixture in batches, mixing it in with the spatula. When about
            two-thirds of the flour has been added, the mixture will seem very dry and as if it is
            not coming together. Working now with your hands, continue to add the flour and work the
            dough together until it becomes smooth, soft to the touch and pliable. Gather the dough
            into a ball, wrap in plastic wrap and refrigerate at least <time>30 minutes and up to 2
                days</time> . </step6>
        <step7> Assemble the cookies: Position a rack in the middle of the oven and preheat to 350
            degrees. Line two large, rimmed baking sheets with parchment paper. In a small bowl,
            whisk together the remaining egg yolk, honey and water for the egg wash. </step7>
        <step8> Divide the dough into four equal pieces; each piece should weigh about 240 grams.
            Divide each section into 12 pieces, about <mass>20 grams</mass> each, and roll into
            balls. You should wind up with <size>48 balls</size>. Do the same for the pineapple
            filling with each ball weighing about <mass>8 grams</mass>; it helps to scoop it using a
                    <measure><num num="1">1</num>-<unit>teaspoon</unit> measure</measure>. </step8>
        <step9> Place a dough ball in one hand and flatten with the edge of your other palm to form
            a circle about 2 inches in diameter. Place a ball of filling in the center, and fold the
            edges of the dough over and around the filling, then roll it into a golf-ball-size ball.
            Arrange the tarts one-inch apart on one of the prepared baking sheets. Repeat with the
            remaining dough and filling. </step9>
        <step10> Brush the dough balls with the <gred>egg wash</gred>. Transfer one sheet to the
            oven and refrigerate the other. <conditon>Bake for <time>18 to 20 minutes</time>, or
                until golden brown, rotating halfway through baking.</conditon>
        </step10>
        <step11> Transfer the tarts to a wire rack and let cool completely. Repeat the baking and
            cooling with the remaining tarts. </step11>
        <step12>Serve at room temperature.</step12></steps>
</root>
