<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- what -->
<root>
    <title>Country Loaf (Pain de Campagne)</title>

    <authorinfo><name part="first">Deb</name>
        <name part="last">Lindsey</name> for <publisher>The Washington Post</publisher></authorinfo>

    <date>SEP 10, 2014</date>
    <prep>Washington author Sam Fromartz has been making sourdough variations of this yeast bread
        for years. Here, he adds fermented cider for flavor. A mild beer may be substituted; an IPA
        would be too bitter. The loaf is sized to last a few days. The optional tablespoon of water
        is to compensate for the variable absorption of the rye and whole-wheat flours. You'll need
        a colander, a pastry cloth or clean dish towel and a covered cast-iron or enameled cast-iron
        pot. Make Ahead: The dough needs four 20-minute rests, plus an 8-to-24-hour stay in the
        refrigerator and a final 1 1/2-hour rise.</prep>

    <storage>Storage Notes: Store the cooled loaf in a paper bag for a day, and store in a plastic
        bag for a few days after that. Do not refrigerate.</storage>

    <size>SERVINGS: Tested size: 10-12 servings; makes one<mass> 11-ounce loaf</mass> 10 to 12
        slices</size>

    <ingredients>INGREDIENTS <measure><num num="1.25">1 1/4</num> cups</measure>
        <mass>(160 grams)</mass>
        <gred>white bread flour, plus more for dusting</gred>
        <measure><num num=".25">1/4</num> cup</measure>
        <mass>(38 grams)</mass>
        <gred>stone-ground whole-wheat flour</gred>
        <measure><num num=".25">1/4</num> cup</measure>
        <mass>(32 grams)</mass>
        <gred>stone-ground whole rye flour</gred>
        <measure><num num=".5">1/2</num> teaspoon</measure>
        <gred>instant yeast or bread machine yeast</gred>
        <measure><num num="1">1</num> teaspoon</measure>
        <gred>table salt</gred>
        <measure><num num=".25">1/4</num> cup</measure>
        <mass>(55 grams)</mass>
        <gred>dry fermented cider (may substitute Pilsener beer; see headnote)</gred>
        <measure><num num=".5">1/2</num> cup</measure>
        <mass>(120 grams)</mass>
        <gred>lukewarm water (80 degrees), plus an optional 1 tablespoon</gred></ingredients>
    <steps>DIRECTIONS <step1><type ingred="dry">Whisk together the flours, yeast and salt in a
                mixing bowl.</type></step1><step2><type ingred="wet"> Combine the cider and water in
                a liquid measuring cup.</type></step2>
        <step3>Add the liquid to the flour mixture</step3><step4><texture>; use a spatula or bench
                scraper or your hand moistened with water to blend them for about a minute. The
                dough should be shaggy yet cohesive.</texture></step4><step5> Cover the bowl with a
            towel; let the dough rest for 20 minutes.</step5>
        <step6>Moisten your kneading hand.</step6>
        <option>If the dough seems stiff, add the optional tablespoon of water.</option><step7>
            Stretch one edge of the dough (still in the bowl), then press it into the center of the
            bowl. Repeat this about a dozen times, moving clockwise to catch all sides of the dough.
            (This should take 1 or 2 minutes.) </step7>
        <step8>Turn the dough over so the seams are on the bottom. Cover and let rest for 20
            minutes. Repeat the clockwise stretching and folding two more times, with 20-minute
            rests after each.</step8>
        <step9>Cover and refrigerate at least 8 hours and up to 24 hours. <observation>The dough
                should have doubled. If it hasn't, leave it on the counter until it
                does.</observation></step9>
        <step10>Lightly flour a work surface. Use a pastry cloth or clean dish towel to line a round
            colander. Dust the cloth with flour.</step10>
        <step11>Transfer the dough to the floured work surface. Fold the edges toward the center to
            create a round shape, turning it over so the seams are on the bottom. Let it rest for 5
            minutes, then transfer to the colander, seam side up. Cover with a towel and let the
            dough rise for 1 1/2 hours.</step11>
        <step12>Thirty minutes before baking, place a cast-iron Dutch oven (lid on) or enameled
            cast-iron pot with a lid (on) in the oven; preheat to 475 degrees.</step12>
        <step13>Carefully remove the hot pot from the oven.</step13>
        <step14>Turn the dough out onto the counter so the seams are on the bottom. Use kitchen
            scissors to make 8 snips on the top of the dough in an evenly spaced spoke pattern, each
            about 1/4-inch deep. Lift the dough and carefully drop it into the hot pot. Immediately
            cover with the hot lid. Bake for 30 minutes, then reduce the heat to 450 degrees.
            Uncover and bake for 8 to 10 minutes or until the crust is dark brown. Try to minimize
            the amount of time the oven door is open.</step14>
        <step15>The bread is done when its internal temperature registers 205 degrees on an
            instant-read thermometer and the loaf sounds hollow when knocked on the
            underside.</step15>
        <step16>Transfer the loaf to a wire rack to cool for at least 1 hour before
            cutting.</step16></steps>
</root>
